Now let us see where to write our programs, where to write C++ programs.
So there are various IDs.
You can use the IDs and also you can practice your programs on online compiler.
So I suggest you to better use online compilers, right?
So if you face any difficulty, you can share the code and we can test it on same online compiler and
it can we can help you better.
And also you can use the IDs.
I will show you how to use the IDs in the next lectures.
If you are already using some ID and comfortable with some ID like code blocks or Def, C++ or Visual
Studio, you can use it.
All right.
So now I will show you where to practice C++ programs online.
So open Chrome browser and here type online GDB online gdb.
So don't select dotcom, don't select dotcom.
Just give space and say C++.
Don't directly go to dotcom, write online, GDB, C++.
If you want to use a C, you can use C also.
So enter now the first link that is online compiler and debugger for C and C++.
Click on this one.
So here you are on online gdb.
Right.
There's a compiler.
No, you can read it in the URL.
It is online C++ compiler.
All right.
Now, one important thing on the right hand side, on the right hand top, you can see here, C++ is
selected right on the right hand side.
C++ is selected.
That is the reason I told you to type on GDB and C++ then.
In Google search it has already shown you C++ links, so we directly came here.
Otherwise if you want to change the language, you can change the language.
You can select other languages also like Java or C language or other languages.
So there are many various languages all available.
So you can use this online compiler for various languages.
All right.
But we are using it for C++, so don't touch anything.
Just leave it, because already you have selected C++ compiler and you can see that so readily available.
Some piece of code is available here.
That is C++ code is available here.
So it is a hello world program.
It will print Hello World.
All right.
So I don't have to type anything.
This is a sample program is already available.
Just click on run.
It will run the code.
Here it is at the bottom.
It has shown the result.
That is Hello world.
All right.
Now, if you want to write something in your program, just as a sample, I will write down.
Okay.
So later, we will be learning about this one.
I'm not going to explain what I am writing.
I just am testing it.
And two numbers then seen reading two numbers X and Y, then z, assign x plus y.
I am writing a program for adding to numbers.
So instead of Hello World I will just modify it.
I'm not writing it separately.
Some s addition of two numbers is print z.
Now don't try to understand anything, okay?
Just.
I have written something to demonstrate that you can write any program here.
You don't have to touch anything just inside the main function.
Start writing a program.
So I have written my code in main function.
Now let us run it and see whether it will add it to numbers or not.
So it's asking me to enter two numbers.
I'll give the first number as ten and second number as 20, and the result is 30.
So I'm starting.
Yes, it is working perfectly.
So that's it, this is a better place.
Alright.
And if you find there are many compilers available, online compilers are available, you can practice
any way you like.
All right, so this is the way you can practice online.
All right.
And if you want to install it in the next lectures, you will find how to install it on your machine.
So that's all in this lecture.
So practice programs here in online.