In this video, I will show you how to download Def C++, how to set it up and how to use it.
So this is an ID I use for writing C++ program.
Most of the students use Def C++, so let us learn how to download and set up.
So open Google Chrome and Google Chrome search for download def C++ with min g w.
So already there.
I have searched for it already.
So this is the thing that you have to type.
Just note down, make sure you are searching for the same thing, same string download dev c++ with
min gw min GW is a compiler.
So when you download dev C++ it's an ID along with that compiler will also get downloaded and installed
on your machine.
So just hit enter.
Then you'll find various links.
Click on the first link that is from SourceForge Dot Net.
So click on this one.
Now here we are on a download page on SourceForge website.
Click on this green button.
You can read it.
Download latest version.
Def C++ 5.11.
EDM cc 4.99.2.
Setup dot x.
Make sure you have reached the same link.
Right.
You should read it and check you are on the same link.
Click on this one.
It will start downloading after downloading install dev C++.
Okay.
It has finished installation.
If I show you the folder where dev C++ is installed, this is in C and program files.
And here is CP.
So you can see that there is also install min GW that is GMU compiler for Windows.
This is a minimal compiler for Windows.
Let us start dev C++.
So English language selected the next then.
Okay.
Yes.
Def C++ is ready now.
Before we start using it, we have to make some important settings and these settings we have to do
only once.
So let me show you what settings we have to do.
Go to the menu and the menu.
You'll find tools on the top, then select compiler options and here few tabs are there.
That is the general tab.
Inside this mention hyphen g.
This will allow the compiler or the debugger to debug the program.
So there's a flag for the compiler which will allow the debugger to debug the program.
So what is debugging and all?
We will see it later in the next videos.
You have to mention this hyphen G or minus G, then go to another tab.
That is programs.
Here, you'll find Jesus.
So for that Jesus wrote X is given.
And this compiler by default it will be C++ 98 version, but will be using the features of C++ 11.
That is that is the later version.
So to use C++ 11, we have to mention here.
So this is what you are supposed to write, hyphen STD.
That is minus STD.
You can delete as then equal to C++ 11.
Then do the same thing in the next field.
Also write C++ 11, HDC, C++ 11.
It can be kept a lot small C++.
That doesn't make difference.
By mentioning this now, the ID will be using C++ 11 compiler.
Now we are using the in our course will be we will be using the features of C++ 11 also.
So if this is not mentioned, those features will not work.
So this is the very important thing that you have to do in the settings.
Now we are ready.
Just say, okay, now the settings are done.
Now we are ready to do any project or write over C++ programs.
So let me show you how to create a new project.
Say a new project.
And Select Console application.
Let the project name as my first.
And it should be created in documents.
Now the project is ready.
This is main door zip file inside the project.
So here, I'll just give a message.
Hello world.
And.
And they should use namespace for code as well as.
And then let us build the project and execute.
Now Helloworld has appeared.
So that's all.
This is how you can open a new project for every program or application.
You can start a new project or else for practicing in the same project.
You can go on writing new code there and you can recompile and run it.