In this video, we will see how to use a debugger in code blocks.
Debugger is used for tracing the program's execution line by line, we can trace the program to see
it's working in detail by checking the execution of each line.
It's also called us tracing the program.
If there is any error or the program is not giving expected results, we can check the execution of
the program line by line, and we can catch that error.
Even for understanding the working of a program.
We can take the help of debugger.
I have used a debugger in few programs in my codes.
So here we will see how to use a debugger.
For that, I will create a new project and I will write down the program.
So create a new project and say console application.
Then this should be C++, right?
The next here, I will call it as my debug.
Yes.
It's ready.
Now here already I have a program, so I will place the program here directly.
Here is my program.
So the program is to find the sum of all the elements in an array.
These are the elements in an array.
The program will add all these elements and store the result in sum, by taking one element at a time
in variable x.
So this type of programs we will see later.
But here the purpose is to show you debugging.
So let us first of all compile the program.
So go to build and say.
Build and run.
So it will compile and build the program and run.
So I'm getting the result as 25.
That is sum of all these elements in an early.
That is one plus two plus five plus eight plus nine is 25.
Now the program is already combined.
Now I want to run the debugger.
So before running the debugger, I should put a breakpoint on any one of the statement.
So I'll put a breakpoint.
It's better to put a breakpoint on the beginning statement so we can see that execution of all these
statements one by one.
So go on this line eight and right click and say Add breakpoint.
So here you have to say add breakpoint.
And then again, right click on this line to delete it.
Remove the breakpoint so you can remove breakpoint like this.
So I'll add it once again.
Say, add breakpoint.
Now Breakpoint is ready.
I have to call debugger.
So go to debug option and say start.
Right.
So the option is f eight here.
Again, if you want to execute line by line, you can use F seven.
So let us start.
Debugger is started now if you want to see the contents of the variables, what the values are there
in the variables you have to add a watch.
So for getting a watch window, this is the method go to debug menu and inside that select debugging
windows menu and click on watch us.
Here.
I got watches and this is already having variables like some and a.
So here inside the program you can see some is there and a is there.
So this a if I open then you can see it is having the values one, two and five, eight, nine.
So which are already given here, but it is not showing x.
So if it is not showing any variable, you just can select that variable right click and say watch x
so it's not available in current context.
And even if it is not showing other variables like some or a, you can select it.
Now, before we continue, let us see what this program is doing.
This program is going to add all these elements and find the sum of all these elements in variable X.
So X will be taking the values that are present in array a one by one, like one, two, five, eight
and nine.
Then it will be going, adding them to sum.
So here inside the watch, you have to observe how the values of this sum and this X are changing right
now.
Let us proceed.
So I'll execute the next statement.
I'll press F seven now.
That is already there and access is still not defined.
Now you can see that X is having value one here in red, then some is still zero and it is on this 14th
line where it has not yet added this one.
Once this line ends, the value of X will be added to sum.
So if I press f seven, you can see the value of some will be changing.
If some became one.
Then again, if I continue X became two.
So you have to watch in the site, X became two.
Now next line, the sum becomes three.
So one plus two, that is three.
Then sum becomes five and sum becomes eight, x became five and then some became eight.
Now x is eight and some becomes 16, x is nine, then some becomes 25.
Now it will come out of the loop.
So here you can see that the line, this this current line is shown by this arrow here, not responding
on this one.
If I press f seven, then the value will be printed and here is the window.
You can click on this and see the value 25 is printed.
So that's it.
This is how you can use a debugger for executing the program line by line and see how it is executing,
how it is modifying or updating the variables.
You can take the help of debugger for detailed understanding of execution of program, and also if there
are any errors, you can trace it and remove the errors.
So that's all in this video.