In this video, we will see how to use a debugger in C++.
Debugger is used for tracing the program line by line.
We can watch the program and see how it is executing line by line.
Sometimes if the program is not giving expected results or it is giving wrong output, then we may check
the program line by line to check to find out where we have gone wrong.
You'll be learning more about the usage of debugger in the coming videos while giving the demonstration
of programs.
I have used debugger sometimes, so even you can do it in C++.
So let us see how to use a debugger so far.
So for that, first of all, I will create a project and I will write one simple program.
Then I will show you the options that you have to use for using a debugger.
New project.
And say console application and it's a C++ project.
Let us name it as.
And say, okay.
Now hear the skeleton of a program is ready.
I'll replace it with my program.
Yeah.
Here is the program.
Ready?
Now, don't go into the details of the program.
This program is to find the sum of all these elements.
Addition of these elements, that is one, two, five, eight, nine.
So it will give the sum of all these elements that's going to be 25.
So let us first compile the program.
I'll.
Let us first.
Let us first compile and build the program.
So go to execute and see.
Compile and run.
She's asking me to save the file.
Yes.
May not keep saved.
So it's giving the result.
That is 25.
No, this is a normal execution.
I have done now one I have compiled.
So the program is ready to run now.
So instead of running, I will perform debugging.
So for debugging, first of all, we have to put a breakpoint upon any statement.
So on the first statement itself, I'll put a breakpoint.
So for putting a breakpoint in dev C++, just click on the statement here.
I have clicked on the number right on the left hand side, leftmost corner.
I have just clicked here.
If you again click, it will be gone.
So for toggling you can just click and click once again it's gone.
So it's like on and off.
So now it is on, right?
So this statement is having breakpoint.
So when I run the debugger, it will come and stop here so that from there I can carry on by executing
the statements one by one.
So let us start the debugger.
So for starting a debugger I can go to execute now this time instead of calling run or compiler run,
just go down at the in the menu options and select debug.
So you can see that even I can do it using F5.
So you can even press F5 for.
Starting debugger.
Now, here it is at this line.
It has not yet executed the line.
Now I want to know what are the values in these variables?
So the variables that I have are some and A and X, these are some variables.
So let us add these variables in a watch.
So for this I will select the sum and right click.
And here is an option.
Add watch.
So it is added to a watch and the sum variable is zero right now.
And a.
And right click say Ad Watch is added and it is having some garbage values.
It's not having these values.
One, two, five, eight, nine, because this line is not yet executed.
Then I have one more variable x.
I will select this and add watch.
So execute to evaluate.
So what is the result of this?
X is not yet known because it has not yet reached here.
My my program has executed till this line.
So the line which is highlighted it is here now let us execute it step by step and see how these values
in the watch are changing.
So you have to observe here this area and here I will be executing the statements line by line and here
there is a loop.
So this will be repeatedly executing and the value of some will also be changing because it will be
keep on adding the value of X into sum.
So let us see it now.
So for executing next line here at the bottom, we have option like next line.
So you can press this or even you can press F seven, you can see there is a tooltip popping up showing
that for next line press f seven.
So I'll press next line.
So it is on the next line.
Now I'm pressing F seven for continuation.
Now after this line you can see that the array values, these values will be changing, right?
It is on this line.
It has not error executed.
So this values will be changing.
C earlier it was on some and already some was having zero so that actually the value was garbage.
Then again, zero is a sign, right?
So garbage value can be even zero.
Here you can see inside a one of the values zero.
So it has not yet executed this line.
So press f seven is now re is initialized with these values here.
You can see this on the left hand side and the debug window you can see this one.
This is watch.
Watching the contents of the variables right now press f seven now does enter inside follow you can
drag this blue color line now some hands became one, an x value was one, now x becomes two.
Now it will be added to sum and some becomes three.
Now X became five.
It will be added to some and some becomes eight.
So you can watch here.
Some became eight.
An x value is five.
So the next after five it is eight.
So let us see.
Next is X became eight.
So some should become 16.
Yes, some became 16, then x is becoming nine.
So then some became 25.
So end of this loop.
And this is printed.
So if you see the window here, you can watch here.
The value 25 is printed.
So this is how we can trace how the program is working and closely observe how the values of the variables
are changing and if anything unexpected found, then you can make corrections in your code.
So that's all about debugging.
So you remember the options that you have to go here and execute and start the debugger, and then afterwards
you have to just keep on pressing next line or F7 and for watching the variables, you have to select
the variable and say Add watch or even you can click on this add watch button and here you can enter
the variable in.
So that's all about debugger and maybe showing it again in some of the programs, how to use the debugger
for that particular program.