Debugging and Visual Studio.
C Debugging is the process of executing the program line by line and tracing the program.
So tracing will help us to find out any bugs in the program.
A program if a program is executing but not giving perfect results, then there may be something gone
wrong in the program.
To find out that mistake, we have to trace the program and check it.
So for tracing debugger will help us.
So how to do debugging?
We will see here you don't have to do any special settings for debugging, so it's very easy.
And Visual Studio.
I'll show you how to do debugging.
So already I have one program written here.
This program is already available for finding the sum of all the elements in an array.
So I have some array of elements and the program will find the.
Addition of all these elements.
So let us do debugging.
So for debugging, you have to set some breakpoint in any statement in the program.
So till the breakpoint, the program will execute normally and it will stop there.
Then you can trace it line by line.
So I'll put a breakpoint on.
The first line itself was first instruction itself.
So the method of putting a breakpoint is on the left hand side that is before the line number.
And this gray area just click.
So it will insert a breakpoint.
And if you want to remove, just click it again.
It will be gone.
So it is just like toggling on and off.
So just click it once.
That's it.
We got a breakpoint.
You can have more than one breakpoints also in the program.
So if the program is very lengthy, you may require that so you can have multiple breakpoint.
So here I have first statement as a breakpoint.
Now let us run, go to debug and say start debugging.
So for that you can press F5 also.
So just click on this one.
It is on the first line.
Yes, it is already.
So you can see that till this line some variable is declared, but the line is not yet executed.
So here is a watch window.
Here is the watch window.
It will automatically pop up and here you can find some.
And just having garbage value means it's not yet initialized.
So this variable, this line is about to be executed, right?
So if I take the cursor also it is showing that the value in sum is some garbage value.
Now let's execute this line.
So for that, what I have to press, just go to debug and here you can find the statements like step
into, step over or step out so you can follow F ten for step over.
If it is a function and you want to go inside that function, then you can say step into.
So for this symbol program F ten is okay, so you can press F ten, so come back and press F ten.
So I'm pressing F ten.
Yes.
Now you can see that variable sum is already created and it is initialized to zero.
If I move the cursor here, it shows value as zero and in the watch window.
Now you can see a new variable, A which is having garbage values now, right?
It's not yet initialized because this line is about to be executed.
It's not yet executed.
If I press F to F ten again, then now you can see that this A is initialized with these values.
So here in the watch window, you can see two, four, six, seven, nine.
All these values, these values are there in an array, even in the watch window.
I can expand and see the values here.
So all these values are present here right now.
It's about to enter into the for loop.
You have to observe this watch window how the value of X is taking these elements from A and they are
getting added to sum.
So the values are two, four, six, seven, nine.
So I'll keep on pressing f ten.
Now you can see X is also defined now and its value is two now.
An X is some assign some plus x, so now two is added to sum and this is displayed.
Two is displayed on the screen.
So if you want to see that window, just you can click here.
Now you can see that two is displayed here in the console window.
Now again f ten now continue.
Now X is gone because it has again finished the for loop now again about to start the fall of once again.
So X is not there in the watch window here.
You can see now if I press again f ten now X is there again and it's having value four.
So if I keep the cursor on x, you can find values for and keep the cursor on sum the value is two.
Now when this statement is executed, now sum becomes six.
So that is two plus four is six.
Now it will print four also.
Then again, next value is taken, X becomes six and sum becomes 12, x becomes seven and sum becomes
19.
Then X becomes nine and Sum becomes 28.
And that's all it has came out of the loop this time.
Now print that some.
So that's all program ends.
So if I see this control that is console window, I can see all the values that are printed and also
some is printed here.
So this is how you can debug the programs.
So whenever you want to understand the working of a program and you want to see it's working clearly.
So I suggest you follow this debugging process so that it will give you a clear idea about the working
of a program.
So what?
All the concepts you are learning, you can check them how the things are happening with the help of
debugger.
So debugger is a very powerful tool for learning also and also developing applications for removing
bugs.
So that's all in this video.