Let us see how to install ex-code on Mac OS operating system see  Go to App Store and inside App Store
search for ex-code.
Already I have X code installed on this machine.
See here is excode options available for updating it.
So if I have to update I can update it if it is not installed and this button will be for installation
of excode.
So you can click on this one and install excode on your machine.
And the other method of installing excode is goto terminal.
And at command line say excode-select --install
see hear the message I'm getting is command line tools are already installed.
new software update to install updates, so already ex code is available.
If it is not available then it will install it once it is installed you can start using it excode.
See here is excode
create new excode project
and let it be command line tool.
Next and here.
Select the language as a C++.
There are other languages also available.
So I'll give the project name as my first.
I was asking for the destination that this product should be stored.
So select the destination folder.
Now the project is created and this is the program file. here already the hello world program is created
so you can remove the commands and here you can start writing your code.
So let us run this one and check yeah.
Here in this window output is displayed.
So if you want you can remove this panel's
And here the output is so you  can extend the size of this one.
So this is the watch window.
where you can see the contents of the variables if you have any variables in your program and this
is the output window.
So you can show and hide the output window from this toolbar.
That's it.