In this section I'll be discussing some fundamentals before learning programming language get awareness
about few things if you are already aware of this.
Then you can skip the section and you can go to the next section.
Mostly in academics.
These are the basics that are taught.
So to get the awarness about the computers  so that we can understand how to use the computer means
how to write the programs.
How do you utilize them best.
So far that these are the basic topics that I'm going to discuss like how computer works than what are the
number systems like binary number system, octal number system.
These are useful in understanding how computer works
What is the program.
Why we write the program how to write the program.
These are the things that we will discuss and I work the high level and low level languages compiler
and the interpreter
This is very important.
These differences are very very very important but then in an interview point of view it is also important
mostly stored and cannot differentiate them properly.
So I have given a very detailed comparison of these two.
Then what is an operating system little bit  about operating system.
So let us start with the topic.