For understanding how computers works
first of all let us look at a Block diagram
It's a very basic thing.
Let us study it.
See there's a blog them off your computer.
Let us see the components first of all.
See this the CPU, it is having two parts ALU i.e,arthimatic and logical veiw
and control unit, CU
I'll explain they're working. The next is main memory and this is the hard disk drive which contains
the data in the form of files and this is input device like a keyboard mouse or a stylus tablet anything
then the output device like your monitor or printer and speakers.
Now let us understand that working see the heart of the computer is the CPU that is central processing
unit or micro processor if you present day processor if you see that is i3, i5 ,i7 these processors.
Now this part processor will have two parts that is arthimatical and logical unit and control unit.
So what is that? arthimatical and logical unit can perform arthimatical and logical operations a basic
operation so a computer can perform basic operations like arthimatic operations like addition subtraction
multiplication or division or modulus then under logical operations it can compare two numbers we can
compare less then greater than or equal to and also it can perform logical operations AND OR these operations
like this written in caps so AND and OR as well as NOT.
So these are the logical operations basically.
So it can perform just these basic operations right then.
Second is CU control unit C there are other things connected like Hard Disk Drive and the main memory
input device and an output device for controlling all these things.
Controlling means utilizing them so for that it is having a separate portion that is called control
unit.
So its job is to utilize other resources.
This is about processor now.
Next thing let us start from here.
This is hard disk hard disk will contain files and those files maybe two types.
Either program files or data files like if you take a example a notepad on your P.C. is a program
file when you open notepad.
It's a program.
So there is a file available
Basically we click on some icon and then the program will start.
But if you look into my computers and folders and some where you will find a program for notepad and
its name file name will be notepad.exe
if you search for It you can find this file there's a program file Now inside notpad if you type something
and save then it will be saving it as a text file so you may be saving as my.txt file
right
So this is a program file and this is a data file.
This data file is used by notepad or generated by notepad.
So finally hard disk contains two types of files program files and data files.
If you have audio files or music files or video files all those comes under the data files and if you have
a music player like VLC player or media player those come under the program files.
So we save our programs kept inside hard disk and that is permenant storage this will be larger in size.
The next if suppose we want to run any program then that program should be present inside the main memory
so that CPU can execute it.
So the program is brought from the hard disk to the main memory.
It is brought from hard disk to the main memory.
So this is a working memory.
Our primary memory or work space.
So programs should be brought here.
Then CPU can execute the program by taking instructions.
Line by line for whatever the programs we run they are brought here inside the main memory right.
Then if a program needs to some data from keyboard or it has to display something on the monitor then
it can utilize this input devices or output devices.
So the program may be taking something from keyboard or remember taking something from Internet or maybe
reading something from the file.
So if program needs to some data it would be getting it from here.
Whatever the result is generated by the program or interactivity provided by a program that you can
find it on the output device like monitor or if any output for it is printed on the printer and these
input and output devices are connected to the system and they have the own memory like I'm sure you'd
like this.
This is the memory belongs to input device and this memory belongs to the output device.
So this I will call it as input buffer this is a buffer.
this the memory and similarly that is output buffer this is output buffer.
So if a program has to read something from the keyboard so it will go to memory area and get the data
from there.
I think it has to be something on the monitor then whatever it has to print it will put it in its memory
area called s buffer, output buffer.
It's not that program directly go and print something on the monitor it will dumb everything inside
the frame that is the frame buffer or output buffer.
And that will appear on the screen now same way whatever typing from the keyboard that will go and fall
inside the buffer it directly doesn't enter into the program.
It will go on and fall into the buffer and the program can read the contents from the buffer so there's
a communication point for the device and a program running inside the in memory now.
So that's it.
One of the important thing we have understood how they work altogether.
So once again I repeat quickly the programs are here.
They have to be brought into the main memory for execution and CPU will execute them by executing instructions
line by line.
And if program requests for interactive interact with the user and users input and output devices.
Now we will learn how that CQ works how that works.
How it understand what does it mean by instruction how can it understand instruction.
So for this let us start from the basics.
See computer works on the binary number system.
What is binary system. why it  works on binary system, see it's an electronic device.
So it works on current or voltages
so voltages are trickally or logically used as a binary.
How, a low level voltage is taken as zero and high voltage is treated as one.
So it is just like if suppose you have a bulb, this a bulb right, this bulb can be OFF or a bulb can be
either ON, if it is ON then we treat it as one if it is OFF we treat it as zero, that's all.
Now if you have seen electronic circuitry like I/C, I will draw it here.
If you look at the electronic circuitry like this an I/C, right integrated circuit.
It is also called as a chip.
You can see the photograph also, here I have taken the same example.
Now just on the integrated circuit it is having pins here, these are pins this is electronic right now.
Through out these pins we can pass some voltages right.
Some voltage.
So in this one particular pin we can pass either low voltage or we can pass high voltage. Low voltage
means zero and a high voltage is one.
Now this it maybe taking in and storing it or it maybe moving it sending it out through this other pin the
other end for how it works and all we don't have to go in detail just we have to focus on binary form
right.
So this one pin can be can be either zero or one.
Right.
So only two possibilities are there.
So that's how this is binary.
So we say does that binary number system and we call this as one bit, we call it -- one bit.
So this is.
bit. Then if I count one two three four five six seven eight eight bits are there.
So this together 8 bit, we call it as one byte. So 8 binary bits.
Now all of these bits are zeros means with the low voltage
So this is 0 0 0 0, this is 0 or all those eight bits are zero but only the last bit is one.
So this will be like this or some are zeros and some are ones.
Right.
So there can be many combinations now eight bits together.
These are forming this pattern.
They can form various backgrounds now each pattern of bits we can take it as an instruction.
Pattern of bits of that is in binary form and we can take it as an instruction how it is treated as instruction
I'll explain I'll remove this and explain you. See if there is one bulb then that a bulb can be either
on or off.
Now if you look at traffic signals and if you consider only one bulb there usually will have three different
lights.
Let us assume there is only one bulb.
that bulb is for only two things.
It can be used only for two things.
The bulb is off means you should stop or it is on means you can go. or in other way
If you say no, no if it is on means you should stop and off means you should go.
Whatever it is ,whatever you like.
You can set it so we can set the rule and you can communicate with the people that this will be the
code
That will be followed.
There will be only one bulb.
And if it is on means you can go.
It is off means
You should stop. Like this we can use this type of codes at many places like suppose Oh Officer
is there in his office.
So bulbs on means he's there.
If it is off he's not there. right? or if a shop is there.
Bulbs is on means shop is open. If bulb is off then
Shop is closed.
Like this.
This gives some message this gives the codes so.
Same thing.
Electronic circuitry is having voltages zeroes or ones means on and off using these voltages.
we can make some communication.
So one bulb can give you two messages right.
Go.
Or stop shop is open or closed like that.
If you increase the bulbs.
So let us take two bulbs if you have two bulbs then what are the combinations possible with the two
bulbs both the bulbs are off.
Right.
or these bulbs on.
or this bulbs on or both are on. so it means
This is giving four different messages, four different messages two bulbs can give you together four different
messages.
So if you have to communicate four things with the people then you can have two bulbs and you can set
them on and off and you should already educate the people and say that this means this.
This means that and so and so. like example in an examination if it's a multiple choice question paper.
Now students want to copy them.
Now if one of the person knows the answer so he can communicate to others for that they already said the codes.
Like if I scratch here it means option A, if I do it like this, rub my eyes, then it is option B.
Like that they can set the codes beforehand they set the codes and they can understand it in the examination
hall.
So same thing.
Now similarly we can use two bulbs for giving more messages.
So if there are three bulbs then what, if there are three bulbs just unscrambling so 0 0 0 people
how many possibilities are there.
So this is two power three eight possibilities are out there right.
So it means what about four bulbs.
If you have have four bolts then this is two power four sixteen.
And what if we have eight bulbs.
So eight bulbs will be two power eight that that is 256 so we can have different 256 different commands
two fifty six different messages messages.
So that's it.
So the computer system works on binary number system.
This bulbs are nothing but the pins.
And If suppose there are eight pins like this on I/C so it is just eight now each pin you assume
that it's a bulb.
And that can be on and off total eight pins can have different commands like 256 different commands.
So messages are commands.
So in the same way this CPU was also built up on messages that are in the form of binary that is low voltage
or high voltage that is on and off.
We'll see more on this one.
I'll remove this and discuss further. So now that we can say that the language of computers is binary they
understand binary language that is in the form of zeros and ones that is low voltage or high voltage.
So all the instructions and the data everything should be in the form of binary so of language of
the CPU is binary so how it perform arithmetic and logical operation it performs operation on binary number
system.
So that I can see that the language of machine or the computer is binary but we understand the decimal
number system.
We are not comfortable with binary  number system we preffer working in the decimal number system.
So in combination with the decimal number system How it is equal to binary form.
Let us look at it a little bit.
See in decimal number system we have the digits from 0 1 2 3.
So on to 9 we use these digits to form a number but then in the binary number system there are only two numbers
that are zeros and ones.
So anything we want we want to understand in the form of decimal.
So in decimal form if it is zero then it is binary also zero if it is one then it is also one then
in decimal it is two when in binary it is 1 2 and 3 is one 1 1, 4 is  1 0 0 ,5 is 1 0 1 and so on.
So this is the binary form of these decimal numbers not based on decimal number system we understand
that this CPU You or the arithmatical and logical unit perform operations so ignores the instructions
ignores commands like zero means add suppose like assume that zero means add the two numbers one means
subtract two numbers two means multiply them like this they are forming instructions so there are some
predefined instructions that are there inside that circuitry electronic circuitry and that is logically
designed to work on commands. so the commands that we already know we have seen that it can perform arithmatic
and logical operations those operations are given in the form of codes and it already knows that which
command means what I have to do and we write the programs in the form of binary so the programs must be present
inside the main memory in the form of binary so each line of program that is an instruction it will
CPU will take an instruction and execute it because it already knows what it has to do for which code.
For like these becomes the codes as instructions for performing specific instruction.
So if you study some machine language or low level language of computer system you can understand that
its instructions are in the form of binary right.
So that's all we end here.
The conclusion of the talk is how computer works computer works on binary number system right.
And why they work on binary system because they are based on electronic and in electronic signal are
either zero or one that is low or high.
So that how everything is built up on binary.
If we don't understand binary number system so to know how it is related to a decimal system we should
understand some number systems in the next video we will discuss about number systems.