So the previous video we have learned how computer works there I have told you that computer works on
binary system that is zeros and ones or on and off but we understand decimal number system.
And also I told you that the code so that its numbers can be used codes for giving instruction or
data or message.
See I'm just going to give the introduction to the number system but there some topic details, how their
conversion from octal to binary and so many conversions of it.
If you want to learn that it's mostly required in academics if you want to learn that there is a
section called miscellaneous you have to go to that section and study in detail about the conversion.
So the videos are available there. Here and this video, just I don't want to waste your time I don't want
to go in detail right now.
So just I'll give you introduction to
Number system.
So let us look at. See basically we use decimal system in decimal the pictures
or figures are symbols are from 0 from 9 total 10 symbols we have. then computer works on
zeros and ones.
So how many symbols only two symbols.
So binary number system have only two symbols 0 and 1 that's all see one thing I'll tell you once
we have finished with the last symbol after nine we used a combination of symbols we write .
Ten, after that we write 10. 10 means to zero and one we are combining one and zero.
So this place has one.
The next place again will start from zero one two three.
So we have finished with the symbol.
So that's why we're taking combination of symbol.
So same way we have only o and 1, then what is the next number , it is is 1 0.
We have to take the combination.
So don't read it as 10, read it as a 1 0 in binary form.
That's it.
So I have some numbers here.
Just look at them zero in binary former 0, 1 is 1, 2 is 1 0, 3 is 1 1, 4 is 1 0 0, 5 is 1 0 1.
So on ,up to 16 I have written. if you want to be strong in the concepts of programming you want to
study it in detail very minor things you should know these numbers.
So some of them you should remember some of them should be quickly able to convert them so that I have
explained in miscellaneous videos that you can learn it next.
What is this.
octa and hexa, remembering a number in 0 0 1 1 1.
its too tough
We need a simple method.
So what people have done to make this a simple octal is introduce so you can take three digits of a
binary number and convert it to octal. no even this also less so they have introduced hexadecimal
means six plus 10 hexadecimal total 16.
So 0 to 9.
Then after that for10 English Alphabet A which is used that b c d e f last.
So there are
Total 16 digits in this one,  figures in this one,
symbols in this one.
Then after that we take combination 1 0, so how to convert this into this one this to octal
binary to hexa
Everything is there you can study it.
But in this video I'll just show you conversion from the decimal to binary then binary back Back to decimal
just to give you the idea.
So let us take an example.
I have a number decimal number base 10 means it is decimal number.
So this is bas 10 and this is base 8.
This is Base 2 and this is base 16 so we write 10 here because 25 can be there in Octal also hexa also
which one it is? Now to show that we will say decimal as ten.
then how to convert into binary.
So the method is we'd find out successively divided by two to get the binary form two ones twoes, two twoes
So 2*12=24 reminder is 1, 2* 6=12 reminder is 0 and 2*3=  6 remainder 0, 2 *1=2 remainder
is 1.
So we take remainder here.
We don't play decimal 2*0 times 0.
Remainder is 1.
So take the digits from bottom to up.
So the digit side 1 1 0 0 1--- 1 1 0 0 1.
This is the binary form. so this is how a decimal number is converted into binary. Then a binary back
to the decimal.
Let us see the procedure.
If I take the same number and convert into decimal form so take the number in the boxes one two
three four five.
So I need five boxes.
Then write this number.
1 1 0 0 1.
Then, at this bottom, write from right side 2 power 0, 2 power 1, 2 power 2, two power 3, 2 power 4
4.
Now 1 * 2^4 + 1*2^3 +0*2^2+0*2^1+1*2^0
...
This is how much 16 + 8
+0, (multiplied by anything is 0 only 0 multiplied by anything is 0)
This is 1 for how many this is twenty four plus 1 So this is twenty five.
So we got this in twenty five.
That is no. system decimal system.
So this how the conversion is done.
So that's it.
This is sufficient.
I have shown you the decimal number in binary and binary back to decimal so like this procedure are
used for converting them using pen and paper.
Now electronic circuitry internally handle these things. right? For humans.
We follow this conversion methods to understand how it is represented in binary form.
So knowing no. system will definitely help you right.
Give you detailed understanding but associated with some other subjects are also there.
So in other subjects it will be very helpful.
Right.
That's all about no system.
See the coming video based on the concept only right.
So you have to be calm and follow each and every video.
If you are beginner then don't skip any video right.
I'm not going to directly start showing you how to write on the program. first you should have some
basics.
If you're learning programming for the first time study all these, watch all this video and you will be
prepared for understanding programming.
All right.
So watch the next video.