And this video I'm going to discuss what does it mean by a program, why we write program  and how it is possible
to write a program.
So we learn about these basic things.
See in the previous videos already we have discovered that our computers can understand binary form
of language.
So there are some predefined set of instructions that a processor or
CPU can understand.
And we have to use those instructions for performing a task.
Now what does it mean by task here.
So let us understand why.
Actually we need computers.
What is the purpose of using computers.
We use computers for performing computational task.
So what does this computational task.
All those tasks which are done using pen and paper.
The computations by using formulas by using any expression we put the values and get answers so we use
various formula,  various steps.
So computation work that is paper work.
So for that purpose we use computers.
So that computation work can also be done using calculator.
Yes it can be done using calculator.
So let us understand first how do you use a calculator.
And then I'll show you how we can use computers and what does it mean programming.
We use calculator like this.
See for example if I have two numbers I want to add them.
First  no. is 13,
And second no. is 27.
I want to add them.
So pick a calculator hit first number 13 and then press plus then hit second number 27.
Then press equal to sign,
So I'm pressing plus sign and equal to sign.
And finally I get the answer that is 40 so you can use a calculator for adding two numbers.
A simple task so I don't need a computer for this one.
That next if I have a list of numbers and I want to calculate average of those numbers.
So I'll just write on few numbers here 10 15 8 6 9 5 12 13.
So 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8.
I'm adding more numbers eleven and sixteen.
So I have to order 10 numbers.
I want to find average of these numbers.
Then how to use a calculator.
Now watch it.
I have to enter or hit 1 0 for the first number.
Then + then next number then plus the next number plus next number.
I have to go on adding them and that's something to be getting accumulated.
So finally I'll get the total of all these numbers like total is one not five for these numbers then
I should also have the count of numbers, total how many numbers I have? total 10 no. i have
that total I should divided by ten then, I get that as ten point five here calculator doesn't
know how to find the average I should know how to find the average.
So far finding an average I should have the list of numbers on I should go on adding them and then they
should divide them by a number of numbers and that is 10.
Then i get the result right.
This is not a simple operation.
This was a simple operation.
This is having a procedure.
Yes there is a procedure for finding average.
Now similarly there is a procedure for finding the maximum number or the total number of numbers.
There is a procedure for searching a particular number.
In this list.
So for various things there are some procedures.
And if you have learned about statistics then I want to find a mean of these numbers or median of these
numbers.
So there is a procedure for that.
If you want to sort these numbers then there is a procedure so calculator doesn't know the procedure
means that the steps involve for completing a particular task.
now how we know it.
Our teachers have taught us that procedure.
So we know the procedure right.
So same procedure can we teach it to calculate that itself so that just we will tell.
We want average.
It should ask what are the numbers.
These are the numbers. and it  should give us the result without asking us how to do it.
We want our calculator to be trained on this one.
So it means we want our programmable calculator.
Yes that's it.
So the extension of calculator I can see on the next level to calculate there is nothing but computer.
Computer is a programmable computational device.
We can define a procedure by giving all the steps one by one to our computer system and we call it as
a program and the program a computer system or a CPU or processor will execute those set of instructions
and give us the result.
So that's what is programming that's it.
This is what we use computers and what is programming.
I have told you no more about program more detail and clear picture about a program.
I will give you my take on a list of numbers.
So these are the list of numbers.
Let us say the procedure the same.
I want to find an average.
So what are these numbers.
These numbers are nothing but data.
This is a data. then for performing average.
There is a procedure right.
So that procedure.
The steps involved in that one.
So those are nothing but instructions so he can say these are instructions right.
So there are two things now data and instructions upon that data.
So program is nothing but collection of data and a set of operations or instructions on that data.
So we have to focus on only two things in our programs.
What is the data you have and what you do want.
What you want to do with that data.
So what are the steps.
What is the procedure.
See without data
There is no need of instructions like instructions are useless.
And if you have just the data more instruction than you don't know the results right.
So these are the two important parts of a program.
So we have to focus on this one.
We have to learn how to represent our data and also we have to learn how to write on the instructions
that will execute our computer data to get that answer.
So this was a learning programming.
Now one important thing for learning programming you should already know the procedure right.
This is the very very very important point here that most of the students get confused.
The thing that learning programming will make them learn procedure no learning procedures are different.
writing programs is different.
So we are going to learn two things how to write a program and how to write what a procedure right.
How to convert procedure into a program.
So a program contains a data and a set of instructions.
Now let us come to the computer site.
See this is all a machine computer machine right.
So let us say it is a CPU now this is my self, now language of CPU zeroes and ones.(binary)
How to represent data in that one? In the form of zeros and ones.
How do you present instructions.
That is also in the form of zeros and ones both the data as well as instructions are in the form of
zeros and ones that is binary.
Then what is my language.
My language is English language so instructions are in English and our data is also English.
Like if I if you asked me to read these numbers I would say 10 15 9 6 8 this is English, numbers are
also in English.
If you know any other language then these numbers are called by different word or different
names are there for them and the figures are also different.
So this is English.
So my data is also English and the instructions are also in English and CPU language  is machine
language is zeros and ones.
This is binary.
This is machine language and this is natural language that is human being's language.
Now we want our machine to learn our procedures so we have to learn in a machine language or we should
develop our machines so that they understand natural language anyone of this right now.
Either way it's not possible either way it's not possible we can't run machine language and computers
are not so much developed that they understand natural language no recent computers they are having
some artificial intelligence that are useful for pulling the data but not for programming it. for
programming it machine should understand natural language so this is not yet happening right then what
we need now we need some intermediate language so that's easy for me on so easy for machine also.
So that's what Here comes programming languages the programming languages that we use like C C++ Java
C sharp VB Python all these languages become under programming languages.
So we learn this language and whatever procedure are we transform them in this form
and these languages will help us to transform that procedure into machine language.
So from natural language to programming language and programming language to machine language translation
is a time.
So this translation is not there.
We learn it, we have to learn it right.
If translation is available then anybody can do programming just you say it will become a program.
So we have to learn a programming language and write our procedures in that language.
Then from this language there is something called compiler or interpreter.
Right.
I'll just write in short we are going to learn that in this next video compiler interpreter will translate
that into machine language.
So this is how programming languages are useful for writing programs.
So we should learn some programming language so that's all about what does it mean by program and why
you need programming.
Let us revise things very quickly.
So you started with a calculator calculator if not a programable device.
Now we want our machines to know the procedure.
Just want given the data we would not know the procedure.
So for that we need a language so that we can write a program.
So what a program will contain data and a set of instructions upon that data.
this are the main part or ingredients of a program.
But this has to be written in machine language.
We don't know machine language.
So we introduce some intermediate language that is a programming language that is helpful for us.
And it will translate that into machine language.
Machine code.
And the program that is understandable by CPU.
So that's all in this video in the next few days I'll explain you what does it mean by compiler and
what does it mean by
INTERPRETER. What are the differences.
By taking few examples I'll explain them, but I have already used their name here.
That's what.