So in the previous video I have already explained you that we talk or we understand natural
language human beings and machines have their machine language and that language is in binary that is
zeros and ones.
Right.
So it is in the form of zero & ones.
we say this is binary language. binary language we can call it does machine language, machine
language.
So that is termed as low level language, low level language. machine language is low level. low level
means actual machine's language we can't understand it.
So when the machines were introduced initially it was very difficult for people to write the program
so it was not common.
Machines were used in laboratories.
It was not used by masses or it was not available at consumer level.
So at that time so the people who develop they used to learn something from this machine code and they
used for everything in machine code form that was very tough and it was very initial stage and then
later they thought like there should be some attempt to make it easy so they introduce some language
called assembly language, assembly language.
So this assembly language was a little easier than binary right.
So this is nobody can think of working on it, except the one who has to manufacture the machine. Now assembly
language it was little easy.
It can be taught and it can be learned and it can be practiced and used for writing the program.
So this was a use for some time right.
And this became a base for conversion from this language to machine language.
So still that is also low level language it's very difficult for learning if suppose a class of 100
student and if somebody is teaching assembly language then there's the chances of learning one student
learning it right.
So the learning curve is very high and it's very difficult.
Like other parts of academic students learn it for some time and they finish the exam and forget it.
So anyway we don't have to use it if at all you want to work in systems programming that you want the
right operating system level programs and on then you need to learn about it right.
So I'll give you idea on that one where this assembly  language is useful if if at all you needed
then this is also low level so under low level.
We have two languages, under a low level that is machine language and assembly language machine language
and assembly language.
In short I'm writing. As this was also difficult.
We wanted some English like language so English like languages are high level languages they are not
exactly like English and they are not more like machine code right.
So they are in-between.
So that is easy for easy enough for anybody to learn so that are high level languages.
So there are a  n no. of of high level languages lots of high level lang. are out there like present day
we are using language like i will name them.
So these are easy to learn right high level languages C C++ Java Python C sharp visual basic Visual
C++ and the list goes on.
There are various languages.
Right.
So these languages we call them as programming languages because we can program and we humans
can program them.
Actually this assembly language is also programming language that is low level programming language
and these are high level language.
So we are much familiar with this language.
So these are really easy to learn.
No doubt for a beginner it is tough in the beginning but when you are used to learn when you learn any
one of the languages sufficient you can learn all of the languages you should learn one language thoroughly
then you can understand all other languages they are on the same patterns now.
And one more thing about this these languages we can categorise them as compiler based languages and
some are interpreter based languages and some are hybrid languages.
What are these.
We will understand next video.