In the previous video we have discussed about low level languages and the high level languages.
No we already know that high level languages are more like English that are easy for humans to understand.
So in the last video I have explained that there are many programming languages that are high level
languages and some languages are compiler based and some are interpreting based and somewhat hybrid
also.
So what does it mean by compiler based.
What does it mean by interpreter based.
We will understand just in this video.
So the topic is compiler vs interpreter.
Then also I will discuss about
Hybrid languages.
So for understanding this.
We should know what is the job of compiler and interpreter.
What are the major task.
See the task of compiler or interpreter
Whatever it may be.
First thing is it will check for errors, check errors.
Right.
So this is the first thing.
Then the second thing is convert into machine code, convert into machine.
code.
So I will write M.C. as machine code, or machine code language see high level language gets commodity
low level language that is machine code which is understandable by machine so compiler and interpreter
they do this job of convertion right and the third thing here is execution, execution of a program that is
running the program.
running the program means you know that like I already told you that the programs are brought into the
main memory and they are executed by the CPU.
So the machine instruction will come inside the main memory and CPU will execute it. That is execution,
running of a program now for these three things let us understand this.
See when we write any program like this the program so I will call this program as a source source when
you write any source code then that source code may be having errors.
So why you will have errors? see you may be misstating something or you might have forgot some statements
or you have not written the statements properly.
There could be some error so those errors are called out syntax errors.
So weather it is compiler or interpreter.
It has to first check that the code, the source code you have written is not having any errors and is
the first thing and if there are no errors then it will convert it into a machine code.
So majorly there are two task of compiler or interpreter they both do this thing check for the errors.
If the source code is error free then generate machine code then third thing, execution of program.
If I talk about execution compiler doesn't take the responsibility of execution but interpreter takes
the responsibility for execution.
Compiler if not involve in execution of a program interpreter is involved.
So this thing's all we will learn in detail right.
So step by step we learn everything about these differences between compiler and interpreter.
So just keep in mind these are the three major issues that are related to compiler and interpreter.
Now let us compare them one by one. For comparison,
Already I have taken some program code here.
This is the source code written in C++ and is the source code written in Javascript.
So I've taken these two examples.
C++ is a compiler based language it just having a compiler is not having interpreter javascript which
is useful for writing web pages.
It will be a part of that page and it runs inside the browser.
Most of the websites if you visit from your browser if you check the code you'll find html and java script in
javascript in there
So it's a common name everybody knows about it.
So this is used in  web programming.
This is interpreted based.
So this is the source code I have written.
This is not the machine code so this can be understood by a compiler and human means.
This can be understood by interpreter and human being so I have taken an example of compiler based language
an interpreter with language now let us understand the differences.
See if I have this program I wanted to compile means translate into machine code that if I give it to
a compiler, compiler it will convert this code into machine code and as you can see that I have done this
program into two pieces two pieces are there.
So like this is the add function, this is  the main function.
No dont we don't know anything about functions right now but I have just written the program in two
pieces.
So when the machine code is generated it will generate two different pieces that is machine code for
add function.
And the machine code for Main function.
So only the thing that you have to understand here is that if you bring the program in pieces then the
pieces will be generated in machine codes.
That is important.
Now this is the machine code generated.
See this is the file first.cpp
So after a compilation we get some file some intermediate files also and finally we get the executable
file and we get first.exe file, executable file.
So here at the hardest I have shown here.
first.cpp and if you call a compiler, compiler it will run into memory and it will take this program fine
and understand and check that there are no errors first thing,if there are no errors that it will generate
a machine code file.
That is first.exe and it will serve it on the hard disk like so you will get a separate file called
first.exe This is first.exe compiler generates machine code that's all if there are no
errors it has generated the machine code. job  of compiler is over.it has generated the machine code
Now next step I want to run.
I said there are three things right checking for errors, converting, no errors, converted. now execution
if you want to run the program now you can run this program first.exe file you can run and you
can run into as many times as you want you don't need compiler now, compiler has translated once that's
enough over now you run your program n number of times whenever you are running your program this .exe
will be used. source is off no use now and in at all you are making any changes in this one then you
can recompile to get a re generated first.exe file and that will be a new program or a fresh or updated
program.
So it means compilation or translation of source to machine code are done only once.
this is the first point and compiler generates a separate executable file.
there's the second point then the third point as whenever you what do you want to run the program you don't need
a compiler translation is done only once because that's the reason you don't need any compiler when
running the program and one more important thing of the compiler is that see that they are few lines one two
three four five six seven eight some ten fifteen lines are there. in this line if there is any error
at some place suppose if I start from here one two three four five, four lines are perfect and the fifth
line is having some error, your program not get compiled. your program will not get compile if there is
any error tho it is in fifth line first 4 lines are correct right?but it has to generate a complete
machine code, it cannot convert it into machine code.
So these are the points about compiler.
Let me repeat quickly compiler will generate a machine code file separate file and translation of a program
is onlu done ones, compiler will not be there when program is running, right, mostly students believe
that compiler will be there at the time of execution compiler will not be there, and last point is that
if there is any error in some line then the program will not get compiled. now coming to interpreter
so for explaining about interpreter I'll just remove this and I change this files now let
us look at the interpreter so for interpreter I have some javascript code don't try to read and understand
the code just some lines are there OK.
These are written in JavaScript now how interpreter works.
Let us see.
See this is suppose a file called my. JavaScript that is my.js and that file is present here
then I also have a program called Chrome that is a browser a commonly used browser.
So I'm using a name chrome here.
So this chrome.EXE is a browser javascript runs inside browser.
It cannot run independently.
Now how does javascript works how chrome works as an interpreter for JavaScript.
Let's see.
See first of all for I running this one for execution of this one.
I'm not saying translation or anything directly I'm saying execution third step.
Remember this.
I have to run chrome and inside Chrome I can run that javascript I can open that file in chrome.
Usually we don't open the file from local machine we get the pages from internet but here if you open
chrome then you can open that JavaScript file.
If you once open  inside chrome then Chrome will be executing this code, whatever it is.
Just leave it what it is doing so this code can be executed by chrome.
So how? so Chromebook as a interpreter for JavaScript.
So now you can see how it works.
First of all chrome will run.
Then if you make it use this file it will take the file then, it will go through this file and it will
translate it line by line.
And after translation it will convert into machine code.
Yes.
And also it will get executed and Chrome will execute it like C++ program and compiler will not execute
it here.
chrome is interpreter for JavaScript Chrome will execute it.
Yes so How  will it execute it will not translate whole thing then start executing, it will translate first
line.
Execute.
Second line, execute third line execute.
So line by line translation as well as execution.
Now let us compare this compiler interpreter C compiler will read the program.
It will be generating machine code line by line only but it will generate a machine code
for seperate entire program and make a separate file but the browser which is an interpreter for JavaScript.
It will not create the EXE file for JavaScript.
So this is the first difference. second difference compiler just translate it will not execute but interpreted
that as chrome it will translate as well as execute.
The second difference.
Second difference, third difference if once translated into machine code now you use  it as many times as
you want You don't need compiler translation is done only once but here whenever you want to run javascript
you should call chrome Chrome will run it every time, it will translate.
So if n times you are executing then n times translation will be done (interpreter language) then here if there
is any error then it will not compile. Here
If there is any error here suppose in some line then first two line definitely it will get executed.
INTERPRETER were not stop because you're just converting and executing converting executing.
If there is any error at any point then it will stop.
So till there it will execute interpreter will execute compiler program runs independently interpreted
program runs in sight.
Interpreter.
Interpreter No finally concluding point who is faster.
Compiling programs or interpretive program? compiled programs are faster because they're independent
as a separate program.
INTERPRETER programs are not fostered because they don't run independently there are an inside interpreter
inside interpreter context of interpreter so they are slower which are easy to write.
If there is any error in a single line it will not compile.
You cannot run if there is any line error in some line then a line till before that line you can execute.
So it's easy.
So to some extent you can see the program running at this place.
Okay there's an error I can remove it.
So these languages are very easy.
INTERPRETER languages are easier than compiler based language like so.
This is the difference between compiler and interpreter. now i will give you one small example.
With this you can remember this entire thing what I have discussed.
Suppose you are making are Chinese a recipe or dish you are preparing a dish so you have a recipe ofa
Chinese dish.
It is written in Chinese that's written in Chinese.
You don't know Chinese.
I know Chinese and English so I can help you I can translate it again translate it right.
So you want to prepare a dish.
Now what are the methods I can translate.
first method I can read that entire recipe and prepare English version and give it to you.
Is the first method then second method.
I will take that Chinese recipe.
I read first line translated it and I tell you and you will also execute it means you are now preparing
a dish.
I will say take a vessel of this size.
Okay you take it then take this this this, you take it, take some water and boil.
You'll boil it so I'm reading in Chinese translating in English and I will I'm also getting it executed.
You are doing it.
There's the second method.
Now let us compare them, first method.
If I give you an English copy then translations are done only once and you don't need me.
When you are preparing a dish 2 difference right and you can work independently.
Right.
Same thing second difference.
Now here.
Every time you want to prepare a dish again you will come more Chinese please translate I will translate
right this one.
And second thing whenever you are preparing your dish I must be delivered to you.
You're not independent.
That's all you can remember the differences.
So if I translate I'll give you a separate English version on a separate paper.
Now that Chinese version you can keep it in check if you don't need it.
You have the English version and you don't need me on that same recipe once again but here you need
me every time because I'm translating and I'm getting it done by you and that all work is over.
So same way this chrome will come inside the main memory and  it will take javascript and translate and get it executed
by Cpu.
So this chrome is myself and this is Chinese recipe and this is yourself for executing you understand
machine code like in case of compiler.
You called me.
I took first.Cpp and converted into a first.exe.
Now you don't need me whenever you want you can execute directly that exe file.
So these are the differences.
Now finally let us talk a little bit about hybrid languages hybrid languages like languages like Java
or all adopted languages like C shop.
Now these are hybrid.
They have a partial combination that is first compiler will convert into byte code then later this is
converted by JVM into machine.
So I'm not going to explain in detail just briefly I'm telling you they have two steps compiler is also
their interpreter is also their JVM acts as an interpreter right.
this is an interpreter.
Why two stages compiler will check what compiler will do what it's not generating machine code the compiler
just check for the errors if there are no errors byte code is error free code  then Jvm will
convert or translate into machine code so two step process I highlighted three things like checking
for errors translation and then machine code and execution.
third was execution.
So compiler just check for the error free.
It's not machine code is bite code then JVM translate into machine code and also execute.
So it's an interpreter so interpreter for byte code not for source code.
So these two steps are therefore providing platform independency or in dotnet languages.
It is for language in dependency.
These are the different topics anyway just to be got the idea that there are some compiler based languages
there are some interpreter languages and some are hybrid which have compiler as well that's interpreter.
The take the benefit of both and try to provide some excellent in features so that all with this topic.
Let's continue with under the topic in the next video.