In this video I'll give you a brief introduction to operating systems there are well known operating system
for formerly people use them right on their laptops or on PCs.
The known operating systems are Windows.
This very famous operating system and Linux.
This is mostly used by professionals or this is used in companies third.
That is Mac OS X is operating system.
These are the commonly found operating systems.
So what actually an operating system is? see operating system is a master program.
It will utilize all the resources of your computer system and provides services to the user.
See these are the components in a computer system like already we have seen this CPU and the main memory
then the input and output device.
So I am showing keyboard mouse monitor printer and network and measurly hard disk right now.
The programs are running here inside the main memory may require these very fellows
all the resources of your computer system or let us draw a
user also here.
User is using computer systems.
He may be using these resources like accessing internet or accessing some files and ALL.
So program user will not directly use it.
He will use them through a program only definitely.
So finally users should be benefited from the resources and the program.
So this the responsibility taken by an operating system and it means the environment it provides an
environment easy for a user to use the computer system.
So even on your mobile phone you have operating systems like Android operating system and IOS operating
system.
So on mobile phone also it's the same thing like you have a storage and the ram that is main memory
and the processor is there.
screen itself display on its screen itself works as an input or a touch
device touchscreen.
So both are similar. now let us know how operating system works. listen when you start your machine computer
PC. or mobile phone or laptop.
The first thing that you'll see is it is getting ready and if you're using Windows P.C. you will find
a Windows logo and you will get a message of starting windows starting on your mobile phone Android
mobile phone you will get a message at the bottom that is Android it's getting ready.
So the very first thing when you start your machine a device it will get ready upon operating system.
See operating system actually is present in the your storage on a hard disk.
So I'm showing it as Windows Windows.EXC like Windows is also program operating system is also program.
But it gets loaded by itself so it will start by itself.
The moment when you will start your machine operating system will get loaded and operating system will
start executing so that your hardware or your device get ready up on operating system.
So this should come inside main memory.
So I will  just write OS in short for operating system. operating system will get ready first inside
the main memory and the CPU will start executing that operating system.
So the very first thing that you get a screen that full of icons and cursor for mouse everything.
All this is displayed by operating system and the operating system is ready to take the instruction
for you or the commands from you.
So you click on some icon for opening an application.
So how it works.
Operating system running here inside the CPU will bring that program inside the main memory and it
will ask the CPU to execute that program.
So that program runs within the context of operating system.
Now it is not independent it's running as a part of operating system.
within in the control of operating system it is perfectly monitored by operating system.
So operating system will get our program execute
When you touch on the icon on the screen or when you double click on the icon on the screen on the PC
program will get into the main memory and an opening system will start executing it.
Now the last thing when our program is accessing a monitor or printer or network anything program cannot
directly access anything cannot directly access.
It has to get the work done or make a request to the operating system.
It has to display something on the monitor.
It should ask the operating system that I wonder display this if something is typed from the keyboard
that is coming in.
And if a program wants that then it should ask the operating system to get that input so programs
cannot access the hardware directly how to handle them how to access them like multiple programs
may be running right.
So one program cannot capture the device so operating system take care of all these things so it will
manage the resources so everything has to be done via our operating system by making a request to operating
system.
So then any program any program but it is making a request to the operating system for accessing the
resources or getting services from the operating system then it does that by using System calls system
calls and we say that these are system calls or we also call it does API but system call is the right term
for this one. Application program interface or system called a program will makes system calls for
the operating system for availing services.
So that's all I have explained you how operating system will start on the machine and how it will help
our program execute. now in short operating system is a master program which will take all the resources
under control and provide services like you may maybe knowing us sports department or library in your
college like librarian will hold all the books right.
He has a control over all of them.
He has the authority to issue the book or claim the book back from a student so he decides who should
get how many books are not for how much period a book should be given we should given to a student and everything
he decides right.
So a better book is available or not available.
He knows everything so a student cannot directly go and pick up a book and take it home.
He has to request to the librarian and when he is returning again he is give it back to the librarian.
So library managers library that is a sources. Same way operating system manages all the resources of
your computer system and the programs will use these resources with the help of operating system.
thatsall little bit about  an operating system so now you should know that there is something
called operating system also between CPU and the resources and your program.
Right.
So there are few things that are done by the operating system during run time of your program so you
should be aware of this.
So this is sufficient for about knowing about operating systems.
So that's all in the section in the next section we will cover a few more concepts that are very useful
for programming.