In this video you learn about a few basic things that are very important for a programmer to know these
things.
So for a beginner This is very much important.
And if you're already familiar with this then you can skip the section and you can start with the next
section.
So the things that I'm going to discuss here is what are programming paradigms means programming styles.
We will learn about this then what is an algorithm and pseudocode next is flowchart then
steps for program development.
Under this I'll be discussing about linker and Loader.
So in this section these topics will be covered in different videos.
So in this video let us talk about programming paradigms.
Let us talk about programming paradigm programming paradigm means the style of programming right from
the beginning of computer sciences.
That is from the beginning of a programming language just high level languages.
There are various styles adopted based on their development and new trends have been adopted in programming
strengths so few of them I'm discussing here.
That is helpful for us to understand the programming approach of C++.
Let us understand this.
see these are the type of paradigms I'm going going to discuss about.
First one is monolithic programming then modular or procedural programming then object oriented then
aspect oriented programming.
So right now today we are following aspect oriented programming.
We are following this approach and in the beginning it was monolithic so how the changes have occurred
and what other differences between them.
We will study about them one by one so I'll remove this and start so already I have some examples here
for explaining paradigms.
Let us start and pick up one by one and study them.
First one is monolithic programming.
This means the entire program code Source code will be a single piece single fine or single body.
This was the early programming the beginning of programming.
So example basic is one of the language that is old programming language.
This used to follow a monolithic approach in one of the video I said that a program contains two
things.
In the beginning videos I have said one thing program contains the data and instructions upon that data.
So if I listed here two things are there data and instructions so in monolithic programming everything is
mixed everything Is mixed.
These are the lines of a program I have just drawn lines here.
I'm not written the code program coded itself.
Assume those are the instructions in the program.
So this is monolithic.
Let us understand the problems with this one see if every thing has  to be in a single body so it
is just like one man show a single person has to do everything right.
So how many people can write this program together.
How many programmers can write? only one programmer.
What is the length of a program.
It can be growing if it is growing more and more it becomes difficult for a programmer to finish it.
It is very lengthy.
Then it may take weeks or months of time for development and if there is a single error in one line
then the whole programming is useless.
So if you remove that line then the program is correct.
So that's how the dependency is going to be broken down into pieces so it cannot be done as a team works
only one programmer has to do it.
So it is just like a painting.
Only one painter can paint it so multiple painters or a team of painters will not make a painting.
So that's why programming was taught as an art work in the beginning.
So the reason the style of programming was monolithic so everything in it is a single block or a single
piece.
Then as the new languages started evolving and requirements started changing and the computers were commonly
used.
Then there was a need to develop the big sized program which needs a team of programmers.
So modular programming was introduce.
So what is this.
So comparision with this one I'll explain.
See when everything is written here maybe a few lines are there that are used here and the same lines
are written here also
So why to write those two lines multiple times
Why can't I write them at one place.
and use it multiple times here like function one I will call it a function one and here if I wanted
more than one time I will call the function one once again.
I wouldn't call it once again function 1.
So this is what I'm writing the same piece of code and reusing.
So the first thing is reusing  we we can reuse the code here.
So what does the function do.
Function performs  a smaller or specific task.
This is performing a major task which is a collection of smaller task.
So the idea here is that you can break that major tasks into smaller tasks and you can define smaller
tasks as it functions.
Each is a function.
Suppose you are conducting an event like exhibition if you're hosting at your place at your college
then you may have to do a lot of other things right.
Making arrangements inviting people right.
So a lot of other things are required, you can divide the work divide the work and you can do it as a team
work.
So event can be organized by group of people not just one person.
So that's how a single person is doing the entire task.
Now you can divide us into smaller task and divided it and that's it.
So each a small task is a function function so that afre called as modules or procedures so we can make
them as functions or procedures.
So this is the idea of modular programming.
Now one more example I give you here procedural programming means if a person is running a shop he alone
take care of the shop so cleaning of the shop opening of the shop and dealing with the customer purchasing
and maintaining inventory everything he take cares right.
So single person handling the complete business.
So it is possible for a small business not here a bigger business so bigger business acquired manager
and workers.
So let us say function as a work.
Another function under the worker and so on.
Now he's manager.
He knows who should do the job and he will use them here.
Manager doesn't do anything by himself.
He will make use of the people.
People know how to do the work.
So functions will perform the tasks and the main function will organize all those functions together and
uses those functions to perform a bigger task.
So manager in a business, sothat the  business is bigger.
You need a team of workers and a manager.
So this is the change in approach right, now
What are the benefits.
Benefit is.
Once you write the function you use it in your program.
This program are also you can use it in other program and even you can share it with other programmers
in other projects.
So reusability of code once the functions is written  it can be used in n number of times second
benefit a team of programmers can develop it.
suppose 5 programmers each  is developing one function and one of the programmer will make
a main function.
So all the functions if you have some 50 function then 10-10 functions can be given to the programmers
and one of the programmer can integrate all of them.
So a team of programmers can work.
Functions can be developed individually.
That is the benefit.
So this has increased the development of programs or suffix.
This procedure of programming under language which became very famous in procedural modular programming
is C language then Next there's the same example does the same example.
Just a little bit more information is there.
Let us see this.
See here functions are set of instructions for performing a specific task.
This is for performing a specific task.
Performing operations and completing a task.
Operations on what? data.
where is data? data is organized here in the form of a structure in C language you can define structure
where to you can group the related data together.
So this is the data and these are the functions.
And if you observe these functions are meant for back to data only they are meant for this data only.
So main function is having data under functions that are acting upon this data.
So this is the final level of writing C language programs where the structures
and the functions does the same thing only modular programming now mixed as object oriented programming
that has come to this.
So from here I can explaining that. this is the data.
These are the functions meant for this data.
So what they're doing outside.
Why don't you include them inside of this one only.
So yes if you'll see here classes, classes contains data and  the functions upon that data everything is
inside the class.
This is a complete class this is the class.
Everything is inside the class so there's a new approach.
So the more the programming was having data separate function separate and an object orientation.
We say that you keep the data under functions related to that data.
You keep them together only and  define it as a class.
So this approach is object oriented and we can create the object of that class and we can call the function.
This is what used in C++ and Java and other languages.
So this is the latest method and the present method that we are following that is object put in addition.
This what we are going to learn.
Let us understand the benefits of this func.
See if a programmer is developing something he can develop a class so that class contains the data and
all operations are together so that entire complexities is within the class only so one programmer will
deal with that complete complexity.
So this work was distributed at a smaller level.
This work is distributed at a major level.
This was a reusable function was reusable.
This is classes reusable  of the data and the functions together are reusable.
That is the benefit.
So this is a little higher level of abstraction.
Now one last point.
What is the difference between these paradigms.
If you observe what we want to do remains the same.
What the software should do remains same.
What is the logic remains same only what is changing the way you organize your program code is changing.
This is everything was that same place.
This is divided into function.
This is a divided into data structure and function.
This is in the form of classes.
So if you'll see the differences differences.
Suppose a person is running a hotel in that is giving or serving for the food to the people.
Now one person is making everything it is a hotel only and a team of people are there who are running
the hotel
so it is the hotel business only
Everything is same the same food is served  and the customers are all the same type everything is same.
This is more organized this is more organized so only the way is how the hotel is working is changing, purpose
and the result of hotel is same. so same way
If you're writting a programmer you follow this approach or this approach of that approach.
The outcomes of the program will be same only the differences if you look inside the program.
The way the program is written is different.
So this is not for the users of the program.
This is for the programmers.
itself. these pardigms are useful for programmers to make programming easy.
And this is the easiest method of writing programming that is C++.
That's what we are going to learn.
So that's all in this video.
And the next video we will see algorithms and pseudo code.