In this video i will discuss about algorithm, pseudocode and program.
Let us learn more about him.
First of all algorithm.
What is this.
By definition algorithm is a step by step procedure for solving a computational problem.
Then what is the program.
Program is also same a step step by step machine instructional program instruction for solving any problem
that is computational task then what is the difference between algorithm and program.
See we have started writing programming recently but algorithms are existing from centuries. people have
been devising procedures for solving computational problem.
This is common practice who are doing this mostly mathematicians where doing it or scientists are
doing it.
So those who are working on some problems studying a problem and finding a solution, they were giving
a solution in the form of algorithm .
That is procedure step by step procedure.
Now we want that same procedure should be followed our machines.
So we are writing program.
OK.
Yes that's it.
So it means first we have algorithm right.
First we have algorithm then we convert that into program.
Yes exactly exactly.
Then as a student if you will study what do you learn here? you learn how to solve a problem.
This is different how to solve a problem right.
So are you capable of solving any problem.
It's not easy to start solving problems.
First of all you learn few procedures then from that you get some new idea.
Then you can start solving the problem by yourself.
You need some skills you have to develop some skills analytical skills or problem solving skills you
have to get it so that mostly you get from various other subjects as well as mathematics, its not purely
completely mathematics various other subjects and it depends on your IQ level also.
How do you solve a problem.
So if you know how to solve a problem you can write it as a algorithm.
It is just like if you know how to prepare the dish.
If you are a chef then you will prepare recipe right.
If you are a chemist then you will prepare a chemical formula and you will prepare an experiment for
chemical formula.
Getting the chemical result right.
If you are a musician you will compose music so if you are a mathematician you will write an algorithm
that is procedure that's it.
So this requires different skills right.
So mainly awareness of your mathematics and awareness of problem solving.
If you have an algorithm then we want our machine to perform that algorithm and get the result, write
it in the form of a program.
So converting an algorithm into a program.
So that's what you should know the language.
So if you know the programming language then you can pick up that programming language and write on
a program.
Convert this into this then, how do you write in which language you write this one?
we can use any language here.
English like language or directly English also
English also you can use here, but people use some formal notation it looks more like mathematical or
more like programming like so that type of code we call it pseudo code. right.
So pseudocode is not defined not a standard whatever you write is pseudo code.
Right.
Sometimes we define our team will define and follow that one otherwise if it is understandable that's
enough you write any way you like but program you must strictly follow.
If you're using C++ then you should strictly follow Syntax, means Grammar of that particular language here.
There is no grammar as long as one can understand if a person can read at least if you are  write
you should understand it.
That's enough. that is a pseudocode.
So analysts or mathematicians who know how to solve a problem will write algorithm and programmer will write
on a program.
So now as a student as a computer science student or person you have to devise an algorithm and you
have to write a program.
But so many algorithms are already available we struggle learning about them only that is sufficient
if you know aboard all existing algorithms and you know how to convert them into program that is
sufficient.
You don't have to invent anything new unless and until you need it.
And if it is not existing.
Right.
So this is the general idea.
about the algorithm watch this program and also pseudo code I gave you for learning programming.
People will first the right algorithm then they will convert it into a program so that if you have
a practice of this one and then later on you have to devise your own algorithm you should
be able to do it.
You should not be new to algorithms.
Now let me write an example algorithm and also for that I will write on a C++ program.
But I'm not going to explain you how that program is written and all just a sample to look at.
Let me write down it.
So here I have an example algorithm as well as a program that the C++ program that is not a complete
program just a function.
Let us study this.
See this is for finding average of list of elements I have collection of elements I want to find out
average.
Read it sum is 0.
OK sum assign zero.
This means put this zero inside sum.
Yes that is the meaning the arrow is showing the direction then for each element x in list so we will call
each element as X in the list then begin sum assigned sum+ x.
So go on adding the element in sum so this portion as adding all the elements.
Then after that average assigned sum by a number of elements though I get an average number then, return average
so if you read you can understand for finding the average of a list of elements.
Add all of them and divide by number of elements.
that's it. how this is written as English not exactly English.
Similar English as it does C C++ program.
If you have ever seen it is it looking like that.
No but is it readable.
Yes.
Then what is this code? pseudo pseudocode.
It's a pseudo code.
So let us make some changes, if i stop writing this.
Can I say colon.
assign, equal to, colon equal to. this is also showing a direction.
Then here also colon equal too.
Yes you can write, you can write, you can read write, so if you want to change the symbol change the symbol
alright for each element x in list.
do mostly we find like this.
Okay you add it.
That's also meaningful.
So instead  of begin and end.
I will say flower bracket yes.
That is also showing the beginning and ending.
No I believe was a square bracket.
OK.
Use it.
So now this is sufficient.
The idea is whatever you write it should be relevant.
Right.
It should not.
One should not get confused at least for whom you are writing.
This should not get confused.
This is how we write or algorithm using pseudocode.
Now the same thing for finding average of list of elements, this is C++ program.
It's a function it's not a complete program just a function inside this.
If I don't get semicolon it's an error, an intead of assignment if I write less than an hyphen it's
wrong compilers say what is this.
If you want to store the value here like this.
If you want to store the value you must use equal to symbol and that is called an assignment.
You must write like this,where ever  if you write semicolon.
It will not work.
So it means you should follow the proper syntax of a language.
Because this is not for you .
You are writing it for the compiler to understand it and convert it into machine code, so you will write
C++ program and that gets converted into machine code or machine language.
Who converts that compiler will convert.
So you are talking to compiler actually.
So you should talk such a way easily understand if it is not understanding it cannot convert it
into a machine code.
So this language is the language of compiler.
So you should follow the syntax perfectly.
That is the reason you have to put some little extra efforts for learning programming initially you will do
mistakes.
You will not write the things properly you miss few things you know not know what errors you get.
Once you start getting errors we will start realizing okay.
These are the mistakes I'm doing so from mistakes you will learn programming so that's all about the
comparisons of algorithms, pseudo code and program.
So I have given you enough basics so that all in this video.
So the next topic is flowchart.