in this Video let us talk about flow charts. flow charts where used at the time and monolithic programming
was there than later on than when procedural programming came the usage of  flow charts was
little redused.
and today.
We are following object oriented programming or aspect oriented programming so the usage of flowchart
is very much less so what does a flow chart flow chart is used for showing the flow of control of a
program.
How the program is flowing.
What are the steps it is performing.
One by one.
So if a program is very big it is hard to figure out how the flow of a program is so flow chart is useful
for understanding the program, instead of
One is reading the program and understanding.
He can see the flow chart and understand how the program is working.
It is just like if you talk about electrical wiring in a home.
Then from there the wires or the cables are moving through the walls.
If you have a plan then you can know where exactly they are flowing and where are the important points.
Everything you can know.
Otherwise if there is any problem in the wiring then you have to dig the whole wall.
You have to dig the whole wall to find out
The problem is there is a proper plan.
Then you can understand.
So before laying the wire so pulling the wires we will make a plan.
So same way before writing the program we make a flow chart right.
So based on the flow chart we write the program.
So this will help you understand the program.
Now next usually when we are using flow chart the program as a scene as three steps: input, process and
output.
We call it like this.
First it takes some input.
Then it will process.
Then it will give output.
So any procedure you take it will have the similar steps like I was talking about a recipe preparing
a dish.
Input is the ingredients.
That process is the process of making a dish and output.
the dish is ready. if you take a chemistry experiment our chemistry experiment that is done usually in laboratories
will have input means chemicals and the vessels or instruments for whatever you need.
Then the process what you will do with that then it gets the desert.
So every procedure will have these 3 things so program also used to see like this.
Now for that program.
We draw the flowchart Now let us look at the elements of the flow chart.
This is a pictorial representation.
So picture are there for representation.
This ellipse is used for start and stop and this is for taking input as well as output.
And this is for processing and this is condition.
And this shows flow of control.
Now draw a few flow charts and show you gives you the idea how flow charts are used and how they are
useful for writing the programs. flow chart for adding two numbers.
See first of all a flow chart starts.
This is a start then for finding addition of two numbers.
We need two numbers.
So that is input.
So we need input so we can give a message usually give the message that print Enter two numbers.
So does a message usually we write that because we are writing a program program should be interactive.
So for that purpose right.
Then read 2 numbers.
So we read them in variables.
A and B.
This is input.
Now we have two numbers and variables and b then next step is process so processing that we have to
do.
We have to add a and b and stored the result in C this is processing.
We have the result in c now so output, display the output so print sum as
c that's all end of the procedure.
that is a stop.
So does that end a flowchart.
So how it's going to work first it in input then it will perform addition then it'll give the output
then it will stop.
So this shows the flow of control.
These lines are showing the flow right.
These lines are showing flow there's a simple example.
The next example I will draw a flow chart for finding a greater number.
If you have two numbers then which one is the greater we will find out.
So in that till here it will be same  we need to take two numbers.
Then from a and b you'll find out which one is greater.
Whichever one is greater.
We will print that greater number so I'll remove this and modify this one so here flowchart starts and
it will take two numbers.
Now we don't know which number is greater.
So then we have to check with the condition that if a is greater than B The A is greater.
Otherwise B is greater so for a condition we can use this symbol.
So here I will draw condition box.
So here I can check if A is greater than B if it is a true.
Then we will print A if it is a false and then we will print B.
Now here there are two branches.
True or false.
So I will take two branches first one.
Let us take it as true, if this is true.
And second one if it is false.
So if it is true then we will print a value a print a simply I will say A then here false print.
B if it is not then print B then what to do after this.
That's all it is over.
So this is over.
Then finally it has to stop.
Right.
So this will flow and come here and this will join at this point.
So this will also stop.
So this all we can use a condition box if a is greater than B true then print a false means.
B is greater.
So print B so we can look at this one.
Now we will see one more flowchart for printing numbers from 1 to 10.
So I will remove this and draw flowchart for printing numbers from
from 1 to 10.
So for printing we have to do two things one is print.
Second is count like 1 print, 2 print and 3 print so counting as well as printing two things we have to do so keep
in mind.
i will draw it let us start this as a starting point of a flow chart.
Now next we have to take any input.
No.
We already know what we have to print numbers from 1 to10.
So there is no input than initially we should have some counter for counting as we are printing
from one onwards.
So we need something starting from 1 onwards.
So for that we take a counter.
So this is a process so in processing we will take i.
That is initially it is one for first time.
it will be 1 so we will be printing it right now.
Next we will print this one.
So print means output so print i, so first time it will be printing one next.
After this I should change it to 2.
If it is one then it should increase by 1.
So how to increase it by 1.
So this is again a process.
It is not input output.
So whatever I value is in that add 1and store the result in i
So this will increase the value of i by one in the next I have to print again.
So again print and again increase again print and again increase how long.
As long as I is less than or equal to 10.
So is I equal to 10 now or is it less then.
Yes it is less than, so how to  check.
Checking condition box.
So here again we need a condition box.
So here inside this condition what we will check if i is less than or equal to 10.
If yes we will print the again and increment.
So if yes that is true, if this true then go here again start.
So this is like a loop.
This like a loop it will go there and again start and go there again stop how long it will be go on
repeating as long as this is true how long that is true.
If I is less than or equal to 10 so when I becomes eleven we should not print so false if it is a false
means.
This is false we should stop ,this  is stop so that's all the flowchart for printing numbers from
1 to 10.
This is how flow charts values in early days of programming but still in academic.
So this is being used this is being taught initially but it is not much useful later on.
But initially for understanding programming this is little helpful.
So that's all about the flowchart and next video we will see what are the steps involved for writing and
compiling and executing a program.
So step four development and execution of a program.