this is a important video.here we will
the steps involved in development and execution of a program so development and execution of a
program.
So what are the steps we will learn about those steps in detail.
So we will not be learning again and again but we will be using these steps every time when we are writing
an program.
So what are the steps involve let us see. first step is editing.
Second is compiling third linking libraries then loading and execution.
So let us pick up the first one.
Editing means typing a program. where do you type the program so you can type a program in any text editor but
after typing you have to compile link and also you will be executing.
So that is difficult.
So we want all these things at one place editing a program compiling a program linking libraries loading
and execution all these should be together at one place.
So what is that place.
So the softwares are available for performing all these things together at one place those software are
called as I D E integrated development environment development involves these things so integrated means
all these things together at one place.
So I.DE is out there so we use IDE for programming whether it is C language C++ Java any language
we use I.DE. so for every language there is a different IDE available and some IDE are there for all
programming languages.
So to name a few ideas for C++ we have I.DE. that is turbo C++.
This works for C language as well as a C++.
Then we have devC++, Dev CPB.
This also for C++ as well as C languages both the languages which supports right and Xcode, codeblocks
and Eclipse, visual studio.
This is from Microsoft.
So so on. SO many IDE are available these are available provided by different software vendor.
So software development companies they have their own version of IDE whichever what you are comfortable
you can use that if you are very new to programming then you can select Dev C++ right.
And if you're using Mac machine then you can go for X code ot codeblocks you can use any of these
IDE which are what you work on.
Right.
Mostly in India in colleges they use Turbo C++ for teaching C C++ programming.
The students in the college laboratory.
They use this one or else they use a Linux upon Linux.
Also you can use the GCC compiler.
I am using x code in my course.
The reason of using x Code is is easy for explanation purpose right.
But in the next section you will find how to install all these things not a few more things when you
install any one of these.
You will also get A compiler along with that or in some cases for some I.D. You have to install compilers
separately IDE separate compilers separate and you have to integrate that compiler with the IDE .
You have to do it and in some cases when you install IDEit will also install compiler.
So setup an installation part is shown in the next section so from there you can learn and you can set
up your own environment for development.
So in that IDE write the program.
So example program already you have taken here.
Suppose I have written the program so editing is over.
So we have finished  with editing now next compiling.
I'll remove this next step is compiling suppose I have written this program I'm not going to explaining
the program so this will be going in the next section.
So just a program is there, a C++ program.
Suppose I have written the program and file name is first.cpp this is a C++ program
file
If I type this in IDE edit it I should save it.
So if it is saved then it will be on the hard disk
So here it is on the hard disk.
So I have written a program so it is saved in a file.
that is first.cpp so there's a source code and c++ compiler based language.
So next thing to have to do compile it so if I call the compiler from IDE options will be available
you can call the compiler and if you call the compiler compiler will convert this into machine code
and let us say it gives first.exe file on window Based machine that EXE extension depends on Windows
based machine.
Most of the user who use Windows so I'm using extension.exe.
It means executable file.
Now how that exe file looks like see in my program there are two pieces.
One is a function called Max and another is a function called main and at the end inside main and I should have
written zero because it is returning.
So there are two functions max function and main function so machine codelooks like this.
This is Max function machine code of Max.
And this is main function machine code of main.
So two pieces of code will be there that this is a separate file.
So here are file will be stored on the hard disk that is first.exe and this is a machine code
file.
Let us say that is generated who generated that Compiler, Compiler will convert this .
If there are no errors here.
If there are any errors it will highlight and show you the errors and ask you to remove them.
If you have removed them perfectly then you get that file.
So compilation is over now.
Next thing this is a during compilation along with the compilation only.
This is over.
Now we will pickup this linking of library.
What is this ? see for writing the programs.
We need a lot of things that are actually available inside the language.
So language provide some built in  code element code that makes it easy for us to write the programs.
If that ready made code is not there then you have to do a lot of work before even doing a smaller task
like one thing as a reading something from the keyboard  or printing something on the monitor.
Right.
Saving something in a file.
So in mathematical operations like the Cos and sin. log calculating these things.
So for various operation build in functions or classes are available in C++ that are available in header
files or library files.
So there's a header file we include and supporting with this one is a library file that is having
the machine code readily available.
So let me show you here in my program.
See all these things are my own means.
I have defined them.
Then what does this c out std, c out.
this is a build in object level  in C++ that is useful for printing.
If you look inside the main function these are the variables.
This is a max function where is Max.
Here is Max then C already C out.
It is there iostream.
I have included it so machine code for that C out should also be included right.
So yes that will also be included in my first.exe.
This is the machine code for c out machine code for c in and many more.
Whatever available here iosteam.h so iostream is the header file  and that is
supported by Library file.
So when you are using the library means the machine code of the library will be copied in
your exe file.
That's it.
So this process is called us linking of libraries that libraries link with your program.
So link means file is not linked the contend is so far copied in here.
EXE file and this is one of the important thing  which ever the function that you're using their machine
code will be copied in your file.
Actually the header file you use entire header if I will be copied it fine.
So we should be careful if you're not using.
Don't include the header files.
This is all.
So now the exe is ready.
This is done after the compilation along with the compilation process everything is already there.
Right.
Now.
File is already exe program is ready so till here.
Development work is over.
So this is development closed.
Now 2 steps for execution booster for execution.
Now I want to run the program so far running the program.
First of all this exefile the content that is machine code should be brought into the main memory.
I've been telling you this in the previous videos also so it should be brought into the main memory.
So does this is the main memory.
So this main memory we will study a little bit that main memory is divided in two three logical sections
and it is used.
So there are three Section One is the code section.
Another one is a stack from the top and this middle one is a heap so it is divided into three sections
sometimes for explanation I write stock here and him.
So basically there are three sections right  where there they are.
That is a different thing.
So let us see how it will run. for running the program.
This program code machine code has to be brought into the main memory which area code section.
So all this machine code will be copied in this code section Max machine or main machine code.
And so on.
So I don't have space to show all. for that machine code copied.
This is called us loading bringing up program from hard disk to the main memory for getting it executed
by CPU.
This process is called loading bringing it here inside the main memory.
It's loading.
So this loading process is also important process and while loading whatever the arrangements are required
that are done.
So that arrangement.
We don't have to go in detail that is called as relocation.
So all of these things are done by operating system operating system will bring that from
hard disk to the main memory.
I'm not showing that in this picture it is that in the memory already  it is that operating system is running
so it will bring the program into the main memory right.
Then after bringing it it will ask the CPU to start executing the program from the first line.
So here is the main function so it will give the address of the main function and CPU will start executing
that program and that machine code will execute and it will utilize all the functions whatever the machine
code is it will run
So that's about execution now.
Little bit more toward the execution.
Now last step I'm showing.
Once the CPU is given their address it will start executing.
So if you look into the program this is an instruction, instruction this is instruction this is an instruction
this is an instruction but this ABC is a data variable, X Y are the variable.
This is variable.
These are the variables.
Now for the variables also space should be there.
So for the variable space is taken here inside stack.
This is taken inside stack right.
So those variables will be created inside the stack during execution of a program that are created there
inside.
So stack is useful for variable creation and code section is useful for program itself.
Heap. what is the use of heap.
It is used for dynamic memory allocation.
So we are going to learn more about this stack.
heap and all in later sections we will learn about this in detail.
This is sufficient here.
Just the introduction that there is something called stag this something called Code section and heap
that is sufficient so that's all about the steps for development and execution of a program.
So this is how a program has developed and executed it now will be using IDEand we will writting .
the programs.
This is all behind the scene so we don't see all these things just we type the program in.
So this is what all happening at the background.
So that's all in this video and that's all in this section next section.
As for setting up an IDE how to  install Xcord and chord blocks and devC++.
I have shown that if you are already aware you already have of environment already have an IDE then
you can skip that and you can directly start from next section.